Guide to the DeWitt C. Wheeler Photographs and Other Material 1831-1928 (bulk circa 1880?) PR 417
New-York Historical Society
DeWitt C. Wheeler photographs and other material
1831-1928 (bulk circa 1880?)
New-York Historical Society
Wheeler, DeWitt C. (photographer)
PR 417
.84 Linear feet in two oversize document boxes
The collection primarily includes 81 photographs by DeWitt C. Wheeler, a New York photographer. The bulk of these date from circa 1880 and document the buildings on certain blocks along the Bowery, Elm, Elizabeth, Marion, Mott, and Mulberry streets in lower Manhattan in the area of what is now known as Nolita and Little Italy, and along Centre Street south of Canal Street. The collection also holds two unrelated mid-19th century books and advertising ephemera from 1928.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format and related subject matter.
Biographical / Historical
DeWitt C. Wheeler was a New York City-based photographer with a studio at 1215 Broadway.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift, Martha Lieblich, 2021
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily includes 81 photographs by DeWitt C. Wheeler. The bulk of these date from circa 1880 and document the buildings on certain blocks along the Bowery, Elm, Elizabeth, Marion, Mott, and Mulberry streets in lower Manhattan in the area of what is now known as Nolita and Little Italy, and along Centre Street south of Canal Street. It appears these photos were taken around the time elevated train tracks were being constructed in the area and the photographer captures images of the buildings, storefronts, and signage of the time, with some presence of demolition and construction.
The collection also includes some other unrelated items, including two 19th century books and advertising ephemera from 1928.
Photographs.; Lower Manhattan (New York, N.Y.)
- Bowery, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Two photos spanning 168-174 Bowery, with elevated tracks in front of storefronts.
- Elm Street, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  11 photos. The portion of the street included is now part of Lafayette Street. Includes corner of Elm & Broome streets, with odd number addresses running from 187-205. No even numbered addresses. 191 Elm is the rear of Hoffman's Marion cafe; see the Marion Street folder for front view on Marion. Some duplicates.
- Elizabeth Street, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  13 photos. Includes odd number addresses spanning 155-161 Elizabeth, with front and rear views (demolition behind 155-161) and even number addresses 154-164. Some duplicates.
- Marion Street, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  15 photos. The stretch of street in the photos is now called Cleveland Place. Includes corner of Broome and Marion. Includes odd number addresses spanning 7-11 and even number addresses 8-26, ending at intersection with Elm. Includes front of Hoffman's Marion Cafe (rear view on Elm Street). Some duplicates.
- Mott Street, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  6 photos. Includes odd number addresses spanning 185-193 Mott. No even addresses. Some duplicates.
- Mulberry Street, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  15 photos. Includes odd number addresses spanning 187-195 Mulberry and even number addresses 188-194. Some Italian shops. Some duplicates.
- Unidentified, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  1 photo that appears to fit with the set of photos above, but caption is missing.
- Centre Street, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  13 photos of buildings along Centre Street in the area of Walker, Canal, Hester, and White steets.
- Centre Street? / Lafayette Street, circa 1880? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  Includes 3 photos. One is at the intersection of Lafayette and Walker. Two are unidentified but are likely in the Centre/Lafayette area.
- Miscellaneous, 1880s? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  2 photos unrelated to the rest of the photos in the collection. One is of a large house with road or other construction occurring alongside. The second is of a man with four children, all dressed in suits or dresses.
- Ephemera, 1928 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  3 identical advertisements for Fischer's coffees and teas, with endorsement by the Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America that the goods were prepared and packed as kosher for the Pesach holidays.
- Book: "An Introduction to Mensuration and Practical Geometry" by John Bonnycastle, 1831 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  Inscribed as belonging to William Henry Christie in 1833. Published Philadelphia by Kimber & Sharpless. Sixth American edition from the tenth London edition.
- Book: "Snow-Bound: A Winter Idyl" by John Greenleaf Whittier, 1869 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  Published Boston by Fields, Osgood & Co.